Jefferson Patterson Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Jefferson Patterson Papers 1824-1981 1921-1977
MSS83471
Patterson, Jefferson, 1891-1977
27,800 items
87 containers plus 2 oversize
34.6 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Diplomat. Correspondence, family papers, diaries (1928-1930), speeches, notes and book drafts, other writings, memoranda, subject files, legal and financial papers, biographical material, academic notebooks, scrapbooks, and other papers documenting Patterson's career as a diplomat and foreign service officer serving at American embassies in China, Colombia, Egypt, Germany, Norway, Peru, Poland, and Turkey, and as ambassador to Uruguay.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Beck, William H. (William Hopkins), 1892-1957--Correspondence.; Brown, Katharine Kennedy--Correspondence.; Calhoun, John C. (John Caldwell), 1782-1850--Correspondence.; Carnell, Julia Shaw Patterson, 1863-1944--Correspondence.; Chaney, George H.--Correspondence.; Childs, J. Rives (James Rives), 1893-1987--Correspondence.; Davidson, Howard Calhoun, 1894-1984.; Davidson, Mary Patterson, 1894-1950--Correspondence.; Farley, James A. (James Aloysius), 1888-1976--Correspondence.; Griffis, Stanton, 1887-1974--Correspondence.; Keeley, James H. (James Hugh), 1895-1990--Correspondence.; King, John L.--Correspondence.; Munger, Harry L.--Correspondence.; Patterson family--Correspondence.; Patterson family.; Patterson, Frank Jefferson, 1844-1901.; Patterson, Jefferson, 1801-1863.; Patterson, Jefferson, 1891-1977.; Patterson, Jefferson, 1891-1977. Diplomatic duty and diversion. 1956.; Patterson, Jefferson, 1891-1977. Diplomatic terminus; an experience in Uruguay. 1962.; Patterson, Mary Marvin Breckinridge, 1905-2002--Correspondence.; Rabb, Maxwell M., 1910-2002--Correspondence.; Seward, William H. (William Henry), 1801-1872--Correspondence.; Shaw, George Wilson, 1822-1907.; Sherman, William T. (William Tecumseh), 1820-1891--Correspondence.; Tuck, S. Pinkney (Somerville Pinkney), 1891-1967--Correspondence.; Vance, Edward D.--Correspondence.
Organizations
National Cash Register Company.; Republican Party (U.S.: 1854- ); United Nations. Special Committee on the Balkans.; United States. Department of State.
Subjects
Agriculture--Maryland--Saint Leonard.; Art.; Cattle.; Charities.; Diplomatic and consular service, American--China.; Diplomatic and consular service, American--Colombia.; Diplomatic and consular service, American--Egypt.; Diplomatic and consular service, American--Germany.; Diplomatic and consular service, American--Norway.; Diplomatic and consular service, American--Peru.; Diplomatic and consular service, American--Poland.; Diplomatic and consular service, American--Turkey.; Diplomatic and consular service, American--Uruguay.; Israel-Arab War, 1948-1949--Diplomatic history.; Sports.; Tobacco.; World War, 1939-1945--Prisoners and prisons, German.
Places
Dayton (Ohio)--History.; United States--Foreign relations--20th century.; United States--Foreign relations--Uruguay.; Uruguay--Foreign relations--United States.
Occupations
Diplomats.
Acquisition Information
The papers of Jefferson Patterson, diplomat and author, were transferred to the Library of Congress by the National Archives and Records Administration in 1995 and 1996. Material received from the estate of his wife, Mary Marvin Breckinridge Patterson, in 2003 was processed as an addition in 2018.
Transfers
Items have been transferred from the Manuscript Division to other custodial divisions of the Library. Maps have been transferred to the Geography and Map Division. Most photographs have been transferred to the Prints and Photographs Division. Books and government documents have been transferred to the Serial and Government Publications Division. All transfers are identified in these divisions as part of the Jefferson Patterson Papers except for the books and government documents.
Related Material
Related collections in the Manuscript Division include the Mary Marvin Breckinridge Patterson Papers (see https://hdl.loc.gov/loc.mss/eadmss.ms018021).
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Jefferson Patterson are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1891, May 14 Born, Dayton, Ohio
1913 A.B., Yale University, New Haven, Conn.
1916 LL.B., Harvard University, Cambridge, Mass.
1916 1917 Attended Harvard University School of Business Administration, Cambridge, Mass.
1917 1919 Second lieutenant, United States Army
1919 1920 Admitted to Ohio bar Law clerk, Dayton, Ohio
1921 Secretary of legation, State Department, Washington, D.C.
1921 1922 Assistant secretary, Conference on Limitation of Armament, Washington, D.C.
1922 1930 Secretary of embassy or legation in Peking, China, 1922-1924; Bogota, Colombia, 1924-1926; and Ankara, Turkey, 1926-1930
1931 1934 Assistant chief, Division of Protocol and Conferences, State Department, Washington, D.C.
1934 1936 Consul, Breslau, Poland
1936 1938 First secretary, American embassy, Oslo, Norway
1939 1941 In charge of Prisoner of War Section, American embassy, Berlin, Germany Entrusted with protection of Belgian, British, and French interests in Germany
1940 Married Mary Marvin Breckinridge
1941 1945 Deputy chief of mission, American embassy, Lima, Peru
1944 Published Outside and In, 1939-1941 (Lima: n.p. 66 pp.)
1945 1946 Counselor, American embassy, Brussels, Belgium
1946 1949 Counselor, American embassy, Cairo, Egypt
1950 1952 United States representative, United Nations Special Committee on the Balkans
1956 1958 Ambassador, Uruguay
1958 Retired from diplomatic service
1962 Published Diplomatic Terminus, An Experience in Uruguay (Cambridge: Riverside Press. 113 pp.)
1966 Published Capitals and Captives (Cambridge: Riverside Press. 314 pp.)
1967 Published Family Portraits (Nashville: Baird-Ward Printing Co. 63 pp.)
1977, Nov. 12 Died, Washington, D.C.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Jefferson Patterson (1891-1977) span the years from 1824 to 1981, with the bulk of the papers concentrated in the period from 1921 to 1977. The majority of the items document Patterson's career in the foreign service on five continents, North America, South America, Europe, Africa, and Asia, from 1921 to 1952 and 1956 to 1958. One of Patterson's most notable achievements as a diplomat was his instrumental role in arranging a ceasefire between Israel and Egypt in January 1949 during the Palestine War. The papers consist of eight series: Diaries, Family Papers, Correspondence, Subject File, Speeches and Writings, Miscellany, 2018 Addition, and Oversize.
Transcripts of Patterson's diaries, 1928-1930, document his personal and professional activities during his last three years as a junior embassy official in Ankara, Turkey. There are two copies of the 1928 diary.
The papers of Patterson's immediate family make up the bulk of the Family Papers series, 1824-1978. The majority of this series consists of family letters to and from Jefferson Patterson, the papers of his parents, Julia Shaw Patterson Carnell and Frank Jefferson Patterson, and his sister, Mary Patterson Davidson. Patterson's letters to his mother comprise over half of her papers and provide a detailed account of his life as a foreign service officer from 1921 through 1950. Much of Jefferson Patterson's family correspondence relates to his social activities and obligations as a diplomat. Letters to his mother describing Berlin, Germany, during the outbreak of World War II and his duties as head of the Prisoner of War Section at the American embassy are especially noteworthy. He was responsible for ensuring that the prisoners of war of France, Belgium, and Britain were properly treated according to the rules of the Geneva Convention.
The papers of Frank Patterson include personal correspondence and financial and legal papers relating to the National Cash Register Company, which he owned with his brother, John. Letters written by Mary Davidson concern family matters and news about her travels and the various military posts where she and her husband, Major General Howard C. Davidson, were stationed, including Montgomery, Alabama; Fort Leavenworth, Kansas; Riverside, California; Washington, D.C.; Honolulu, Hawaii; and London, England. Also included in the papers of Julia Carnell and Mary Davidson are letters of condolence regarding the death of Patterson's younger brother Stuart who was killed in 1918 at Dayton, Ohio, while testing an airplane. The airstrip was subsequently named Wright-Patterson Field in honor of Stuart Patterson and the Wright brothers.
The Family Papers also contain typescripts of letters written by Jefferson Patterson and his sister. The typescripts were arranged previously in notebooks in chronological order. The original order has been retained, and the typescripts are filed with Patterson and Davidson's papers. The series also provides background on the family's early settlement in Dayton, Ohio, and include letters of Patterson's grandfathers, George W. Shaw and Colonel Jefferson Patterson. Noteworthy correspondence collected by the family, located in the folder "Miscellaneous" (container 14), includes a letter of John C. Calhoun to a Major Austin inviting him to assist in the evaluation of West Point cadets, 1824; a letter of William H. Seward to the chairman of the House Judiciary Committee regarding the application of treaties to foreign countries and United States ports, 1864; and a letter by William T. Sherman concerning the importance of doing one's duty in "any phase in which fortune may find you," 1878. The general scrapbooks in the Miscellany series also include family papers.
The Correspondence series, 1909-1966, consists of incoming and outgoing letters pertaining to Patterson's personal and professional interests, including typed excerpts, 1921-1949, of Patterson's letters pertaining chiefly to his foreign service activities while stationed at various embassies. The excerpts, arranged chronologically, provide no indication to whom Patterson was writing. Probably used by Patterson to write his books about his diplomatic career, these excerpts approximate diary entries and describe his daily life in the various locations where he was stationed, such as Peking, China; Bogota, Columbia; Ankara, Turkey; Washington, D.C.; Breslau, Poland; Oslo, Norway; Berlin, Germany; Lima, Peru; Brussels, Belgium; and Cairo, Egypt. Among the more prominent and frequent correspondents in this series are William H. Beck, Katharine Kennedy Brown, George H. Chaney, J. Rives Childs, James Aloysius Farley, Stanton Griffis, James Hugh Keeley, Jr., John L. King, Harry L. Munger, Maxwell M. Rabb, S. Pinkney Tuck, and Edward D. Vance.
The Subject File, 1946-1978, consists primarily of correspondence, memoranda, invitations, and receipts pertaining mainly to Patterson's life after his retirement. The series reflects his interest in art and sports, his philanthropic contributions to various organizations and causes, his active involvement with the Republican party, and the operation of his farm in St. Leonard, Maryland, where he raised tobacco and Aberdeen/Angus cattle.
The Speeches and Writings File, 1923-1971, contains speeches, book drafts, notes and related material, and other writings. The majority of the series is made up of drafts and notes of Patterson's books Diplomatic Duty and Diversion and Diplomatic Terminus and an unpublished work, "Flashbacks and Reflections."
The final series, Miscellany, 1894-1977, contains correspondence, financial and legal papers, notes and recollections, academic notebooks, and scrapbooks. The academic file consists mainly of notebooks documenting Patterson's business and law studies at Harvard University. The ambassador and diplomatic service file, which overlaps with the Correspondence and Subject File series, includes a wide variety of material, such as clippings, correspondence, and printed matter documenting Patterson's personal and professional activities. Much of the material in the ambassador file relates to Patterson's service as United States representative to the United Nations Special Committee on the Balkans, 1950-1952. His notes and recollections provide a vivid account of the work of that committee. Financial and legal papers document Patterson's personal business interests and expenditures.
The 2018 Addition spans from 1909 to 1981 with the bulk of the items concentrated from 1941 to 1977. Papers in the 2018 Addition complement the initial portion of the collection and consist mainly of correspondence, family papers, and scrapbooks. The correspondence and scrapbooks pertain chiefly to Patterson's personal and professional endeavors. The majority of the correspondence, 1953-1955, relates to Patterson's career and his wish to be considered for another diplomatic posting. The scrapbooks also include letters pertaining to the books Patterson wrote about his diplomatic career.
Organization of the Papers
The collection is arranged in eight series:
Diaries, 1928-1930
Family Papers, 1824-1978
Correspondence, 1909-1966
Subject File, 1946-1978
Speeches and Writings File, 1923-1971
Miscellany, 1894-1977
2018 Addition, 1909-1981
Oversize, 1934-1950
Container List
- Diaries, 1928-1930 (Box 1-2)
  Typescripts of diaries chronicling Patterson's activities as a foreign service official in Ankara, Turkey.
  Arranged chronologically.
  - 1928, (6 folders) (Box 1)
  - 1929
    - Feb. 27-Apr. 19
    - Apr. 20-Dec. 19, (3 folders) (Box 2)
  - 1930, (4 folders)
- Family Papers, 1824-1978 (Box 3-24)
  Correspondence, typescripts of letters, financial and legal papers, clippings, and printed matter relating to various members of Patterson's family.
  Arranged alphabetically by name of family member and therein chronologically. Papers of Julia Shaw Patterson Carnell, Mary Patterson Davidson, Frank Jefferson Patterson, Stuart Patterson, and Jefferson Patterson are arranged alphabetically by type of material and therein chronologically.
  - Carnell, Julia Shaw Patterson (mother) (Box 3)
    - Correspondence with family
      - Carnell, H. G. ("Harry"), 1908
      - Davidson, Howard C., 1922-1929, 1940-1943
      - Davidson, Mary Patterson
        - 1901-1902, 1908-1925, (7 folders)
        - 1926-1944, undated, (5 folders) (Box 4)
      - Miscellaneous, 1884, 1890, 1903-1943, undated, (2 folders)
      - Patterson, Frank Jefferson, 1889-1898, undated
      - Patterson, Jefferson (Box 5)
        - 1901-1923, (10 folders)
        - 1924-1926, (9 folders) (Box 6)
        - 1927-1928, (8 folders) (Box 7)
        - 1929-1939, (6 folders) (Box 8)
        - 1940
          - Jan.-May, (2 folders)
          - June-Dec., (2 folders) (Box 9)
        - 1941-1943, (6 folders)
        - 1944, undated, (2 folders) (Box 10)
      - Patterson, Mary Marvin Breckinridge, 1940-1944
      - Patterson, Stuart, 1901, 1908-1918, undated
    - Correspondence with others
      - General, 1888-1890, 1902-1943, undated, (5 folders)
      - Letters of condolence, 1901, 1918, undated, (6 folders) (Box 11)
    - Miscellaneous, 1889-1906, 1915-1944, undated, (3 folders) (Box 12)
  - Davidson, Howard C. (brother-in-law), 1926, 1933-1963
  - Davidson, Mary Patterson (sister)
    - Correspondence with family
      - Davidson, Howard C., 1941-1943
      - Miscellaneous, 1906, 1922-1941, 1949, undated
      - Patterson, Jefferson
        - 1906-1907, 1913-1928, 1937-1945, (4 folders)
        - 1946-1950, undated, (2 folders) (Box 13)
      - Patterson, Stuart, 1915
      - Typescripts, 1922-1945, (6 folders)
    - Correspondence with others (Box 14)
      - General, 1917-1918, 1939-1949, undated
      - Letters of condolence, 1918
    - Miscellaneous, 1914, undated
  - Dixon, Mary L. (aunt), 1921-1923, 1935-1948, undated
  - Miscellaneous, 1824, 1864-1868, 1878, 1890, 1896-1901, 1930, 1937-1951, 1972, undated
  - Patterson, Frank Jefferson (father)
    - Correspondence with family
      - Miscellaneous, 1879, 1895-1901
      - Patterson, John H., 1897-1900, undated
      - Patterson, Stephen J., 1895-1901
    - Correspondence with others
      - 1889-1898, (2 folders)
      - 1899-1901, undated, (6 folders) (Box 15)
    - Miscellaneous, 1893-1900, undated
  - Patterson, Jefferson (grandfather), 1843
  - Patterson, Jefferson
    - Correspondence
      - Breckinridge, Isabella, 1940-1959, undated, (2 folders)
      - Carnell, Julia Shaw Patterson, 1913-1930, 1939-1944, undated, (7 folders) (Box 16)
      - Darling, Frances C., 1913-1928, 1939-1943, 1951, 1960-1975, undated
      - Davidson, Howard C., 1921-1930, 1940-1963, undated (Box 17)
      - Davidson, Mary Patterson, 1912-1950, undated, (2 folders)
      - Miscellaneous, 1909-1977, undated, (6 folders)
      - Patterson, Edith McClure, 1948-1962, undated, (2 folders) (Box 18)
      - Patterson, John McClure, 1962-1977
      - Patterson, Mary Marvin Breckinridge, 1939-1966, undated, (2 folders)
      - Patterson, Robert P., 1959-1977
      - Patterson, Stuart, 1911-1918
      - Patterson, William P. and family, 1948-1977, (2 folders)
      - Shaw, George W. and family, 1943-1977, (2 folders)
    - Typescripts of correspondence (Box 19)
      - 1913-1926, (8 folders)
      - 1927-1932, (8 folders) (Box 20)
      - 1933-1937, (8 folders) (Box 21)
      - 1938-1941, (7 folders) (Box 22)
      - 1942-1949, (5 folders) (Box 23)
  - Patterson, John H. (uncle)
    - Correspondence with family, 1884-1903, undated, (2 folders)
    - Correspondence with others, 1897-1902, 1918
  - Patterson, Julia J. (grandmother), 1878-1881, 1890-1895, undated
  - Patterson, Mary Marvin Breckinridge (wife), 1940-1978, undated (Box 24)
  - Patterson, Stuart (brother)
    - Correspondence with family
      - Carnell, Julia Shaw Patterson, 1914-1918, undated
      - Miscellaneous, 1915
      - Patterson, Jefferson, 1906, 1914, undated
    - Correspondence with others, 1908-1918, undated
    - Miscellaneous, 1904-1905, 1914-1918, undated
  - Shaw, George W. (grandfather), 1890-1891, 1906, undated
- Correspondence, 1909-1966 (Box 24-40)
  Correspondence, memoranda, and cablegrams, between Patterson and his colleagues, friends, government officials, and the general public relating to his diplomatic duties and his personal activities. Also included are typed excerpts of letters written by Patterson.
  Arranged alphabetically in two categories, general correspondence and typed excerpts of letters, and therein chronologically.
  - General (Box 24)
    - 1909-1914, (3 folders)
    - 1915-1920, (7 folders) (Box 25)
    - 1921-1928, (9 folders) (Box 26)
    - 1929-1933, (9 folders) (Box 27)
    - 1934-1943, (11 folders) (Box 28)
    - 1944, (5 folders) (Box 29)
    - 1945
      - Jan.-June, (3 folders)
      - July-Dec., (5 folders) (Box 30)
    - 1946
      - Jan.-Apr., (3 folders)
      - May-Dec., (4 folders) (Box 31)
    - 1947
      - Jan.-Apr., (4 folders)
      - May-Dec., (8 folders) (Box 32)
    - 1948
      - Jan.-May, (6 folders)
      - June-Dec., (8 folders) (Box 33)
    - 1949
      - Jan.-Apr., (4 folders)
      - May-Dec., (11 folders) (Box 34)
    - 1950
      - Jan.-Mar., (2 folders)
      - Apr.-Dec., (7 folders) (Box 35)
    - 1951
      - Jan.-June, (6 folders)
      - July-Dec., (4 folders) (Box 36)
    - 1952-1953, (13 folders)
    - 1954-1966, undated, (16 folders) (Box 37)
  - Typed excerpts of letters (Box 38)
    - 1921-1935, (7 folders)
    - 1935-1941, (7 folders) (Box 39)
    - 1943-1949, undated, (3 folders) (Box 40)
- Subject File, 1946-1978 (Box 40-67)
  Correspondence, memoranda, invitations, photographs, bills, receipts, itineraries, photographs, newspaper clippings, and printed matter.
  Arranged alphabetically by name of person or organization, topic, or type of material and therein chronologically.
  - 323rd Light Field Artillery Officers Association, 1952-1976 (Box 40)
  - Alexis Lachine Co., 1959-1961
  - American Association of Museums, 1970-1971
  - American Foreign Service Association, 1969-1975
  - American Near East Foundation, 1975
  - American Security Council, 1970-1976
  - Atlantic Council of the United States, 1962-1977, (2 folders)
  - "A" miscellaneous, 1952-1977, (5 folders) (Box 41)
  - Becker, Ralph E., 1956-1959
  - Black, Robert K., 1960-1968
  - Brown, Katharine Kennedy, 1952-1973, (3 folders)
  - "B" miscellaneous (Box 42)
    - 1952-1972, (10 folders)
    - 1973-1977, (3 folders) (Box 43)
  - Calvert County, Md., 1970-1973
  - Carlo, Florian and Sylvain, 1968-1970
  - Chaney, Patterson, 1956-1962
  - Chou, Chi Ye, and Chun Kuan Tseng, 1950-1956, (3 folders)
  - Clubs (Box 44)
    - 1953-1975, (8 folders)
    - 1976-1978, (2 folders) (Box 45)
  - "C" miscellaneous, 1950-1977, (9 folders)
  - Dayton Art Institute, Dayton, Ohio (Box 46)
    - 1958-1971, (8 folders)
    - 1972-1977, (4 folders) (Box 47)
  - Dayton Council on World Affairs, Dayton, Ohio, 1958-1959, (2 folders)
  - Diplomatic and consular officers, retired
    - 1953-1963, (3 folders)
    - 1964-1972, (3 folders) (Box 48)
  - "D-E" miscellaneous, 1950-1977, (6 folders)
  - Frontier Nursing Service, 1964-1967
  - "F" miscellaneous, 1952-1975, (4 folders) (Box 49)
  - Girstmair, Andreas, 1955-1970, (2 folders)
  - Goldwater, Barry M., 1964-1965
  - Goossers, Herbert E., 1952-1976, (3 folders)
  - Grant House, York, Maine, 1972-1973
  - "G" miscellaneous, 1952-1976, (4 folders) (Box 50)
  - Human Events, 1961-1969
  - "H" miscellaneous, 1958-1976, (5 folders)
  - International Movement for Atlantic Union, 1963
  - International Student House, Washington, D.C., 1963-1970
  - Invitations, 1962-1975 (Box 51)
  - "I" miscellaneous, 1958-1973
  - Johns Hopkins University, School of Advanced International Studies, Washington, D.C., 1962, 1973-1974
  - "J-K" miscellaneous, 1952-1977, (5 folders)
  - Libreria L'Amateur, 1957-1962
  - "L" miscellaneous
    - 1952-1961, (3 folders)
    - 1962-1977, (5 folders) (Box 52)
  - Marshall, Fred F., 1961-1963
  - Mathias, Paul, 1946, 1960-1961
  - Memberships
    - 1961-1965, (3 folders)
    - 1966-1977, (8 folders) (Box 53)
  - Metropolitan Club, Washington, D.C.
    - 1952-1953, 1959-1961
    - 1962-1977, (3 folders) (Box 54)
  - Montgomery County Historical Society, Dayton, Ohio, 1964-1975
  - "M" miscellaneous
    - 1948-1963, (5 folders)
    - 1964-1975, (5 folders) (Box 55)
  - National Cash Register Co., 1960-1963
  - National Portrait Gallery, Washington, D.C., 1970-1975
  - "N" miscellaneous, 1958-1974
  - Ohio Historical Society, Columbus, Ohio, 1972-1973
  - "O" miscellaneous, 1955-1976 (Box 56)
  - Patterson cabin, Transylvania, Ky., 1973-1977, (2 folders)
  - Patterson Memorial Center, Rubicon Homstead, Dayton, Ohio, 1952-1954, (7 folders)
    - 1955-1966, (9 folders) (Box 57)
    - 1967-1977, (4 folders) (Box 58)
  - Pochstein, Gottfried, 1952-1955
  - "P" miscellaneous, 1951-1977, (3 folders)
  - Ransom-Everglades School, Miami, Fla., 1971-1975 (Box 59)
  - Republican party
    - 1952-1966, (7 folders)
    - 1967-1973, (7 folders) (Box 60)
    - 1974-1977, (5 folders) (Box 61)
  - "R" miscellaneous
    - 1952-1964, (2 folders)
    - 1965-1976, (3 folders) (Box 62)
  - School for Advanced Study of International Communication and Understanding, Washington, D.C., 1958-1961, (2 folders)
  - State Department
    - 1964-1969, (2 folders)
    - 1970-1978, (3 folders) (Box 63)
  - "S" miscellaneous
    - 1952-1963, (5 folders)
    - 1964-1977, (6 folders) (Box 64)
  - Travel
    - 1953, 1960-1967, (3 folders)
    - 1968-1975, (3 folders) (Box 65)
  - "T" miscellaneous, 1952-1974, (3 folders)